Charles M. Kurtz
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Printed Material, 1873-1990, undated, Series 9:
  - Exhibition brochure for Munkacsy's "Christ on Calvary" (Reel 4809, Frame 740)
  - Invitation to Nashville exhibition of Munkacsy's "Christ Before Pilate" (Reel 4809, Frame 801)
  - Kinney Tobacco Company cards with illustrations of military uniforms (Reel 4809, Frame 802)
  - Flyer from Cleveland exhibition of Munkacsy's "Christ on Calvary" (Reel 4809, Frame 811)
  - Press clipping, advertisement and flyer for Munkacsy's "Christ on Calvary" (Reel 4809, Frame 865-866)
  - Invitation to open studio at "The Mendelssohn" (Reel 4809, Frame 1164)
  - "Mrs. Lakey's Picture," review and related essay by Charles M. Kurtz (Reel 4809, Frame 1203-1206)
  - Check list of Erwin Davis sale annotated with sale prices (Reel 4809, Frame 1223-24)
  - Specimen illustration from "Academy Notes: Harmony" by Hamilton Hamilton (Reel 4809, Frame 1288)
  - 3 specimen illustrations from "Academy Notes" by Louis Moeller and Walter Satterlee (Reel 4809, Frame 1311-1313)
  - Poem from The Star "Old Masters," April 12, 1889 (Reel 4809, Frame 1322)
  - Lyrics by Charles M. Kurtz for his "Comic Opera" (Reel 4809, Frame 1290-1292)
  - Newspaper article "No J. G. Brown's at the Columbian Fair," Herald, Feb. 2, 1893 (Reel 4812, Frame 939)
  - Newspaper article "By American Artists, Glorious Collection for the Fair," Chicago Herald, 1893 (Reel 4812, Frame 1065-66)
  - Newspaper article "Almost Forgotten Artists" [account of Kurtz's lecture], Dispatch, March 19, 1893 (Reel 4812, Frame 1161)
  - Invitation and ticket of admission to Uruguayan exhibit, World's Columbian Exposition (Reel 4813, Frame 75-76)
  - Sheet music, Bending o'er a Cradle Low lyrics by Lydia Avery Coonley who corresponded with Charles M. Kurtz (Reel 4813, Frame 490)
  - Invitation and related material for Knights Templar Charity Ball, Illinois Masons, December 12, 1894 (Reel 4813, Frame 546-550)
  - Catalogue, M. Knoedler & Co., Paintings by Robert W. Van Boskerck, 1894 (Reel 4813, Frame 604-606)
  - Newspaper clippings on miners strike, 1894 (Reel 4813, Frame 1097-1098)
  - Newspaper clippings on legal case handled by L.T. Kurtz (Reel 4813, Frame 1130)
  - Newspaper clipping on mob incident in Colorado, 1894 (Reel 4813, Frame 1186)
  - Obituary for William Semple, art patron from Louisville, Ky. (Reel 4813, Frame 1218)
  - Announcement for The Art Institute of Chicago's Seventh Annual Exhibition, 1894 (Reel 4813, Frame 1386-87)
  - Card listing members of the American Committee of the Statue of Liberty (Reel 4813, Frame 1410)
  - Exhibitor's ticket, St. Louis Exposition, 1894 (Reel 4813, Frame 1413-14)
  - Invitation to the Annual Reception of the Art Institute of Chicago, October 29, 1894 (Reel 4814, Frame 51-52)
  - List of cantatas published by the John Church Co., Cincinnati (Reel 4814, Frame 163)
  - Program and tickets for The University of Chicago Convocation, 1895 (Reel 4814, Frame 165-167)
  - Schedule for afternoon lecture series, Art Institute of Chicago, 1895 (Reel 4814, Frame 206)
  - Invitation to exhibition opening for American Institute of Architects, 1895 (Reel 4814, Frame 316)
  - Clipping re: broken speed record for Pittsburg & Lake Erie line, July, 1895 (Reel 4814, Frame 686)
  - Clipping, Kentucky Women's Board of Commissioners for the Atlanta Exposition, circa Nov. 1895 (Reel 4814, Frame 969)
  - Invitation and checklist for Exhibition of Pictures in Oil and Water Colors, April, 1896 Pittsburgh, Pa. (Reel 4814, Frame 1354-57)
  - Cartoon, "The X-Ray, McKinley, No Use Talking..." undated (Reel 4814, Frame 1366)
  - Clipping, biography of J.W. Beatty, undated (Reel 4814, Frame 1367)
  - Clippings: "The Macmonnies Fountain," "A World's Fair Scandal," circa May, 1896 (Reel 4815, Frame 59)
  - Brochure: "Directions For Securing Copyrights" (Reel 4815, Frame 309-310)
  - Clippings, "St. Louis Coliseum Proposition Carried" (Reel 4815, Frame 1195-1196)
  - Clippings, "Art-George Moore," "Society of American Artists," 1897 (Reel 4815, Frame 1206)
  - Checklist, "Collection of Paintings by Mrs. Charles Herbert Woodbury and Mrs. Marcia Oakes Woodbury" and "Svend Svendsen and Sidney Richmond Burleigh," St. Louis Museum of Fine Arts, 1898 (Reel 4815, Frame 1314-1317)
  - Clipping, "Criterion Writers Quarrel" circa 1898 (Reel 4816, Frame 19)
  - Program description, Saint Louis School of Fine Arts, circa 1898 (Reel 4816, Frame 527-8)
  - Invitation, St. Louis Museum of Fine Arts exhibition, "Pastels by Frank Reaugh and Drawings by American artists, lent by Charles M. Kurtz," circa Dec. 1899 (Reel 4816, Frame 821)
  - Clipping, "Art at the Exposition," St. Louis Dispatch, Sept. 9th, 1899 (Reel 4816, Frame 914)
  - Announcement for "The Dewey Reception" by the National Sculpture Society (Reel 4816, Frame 926)
  - Announcement for meeting of National Sculpture Society honoring Thomas Ball, November, 1899 (Reel 4816, Frame 974)
  - Announcement of scheduled lectures for St. Louis School and Museum of Fine Arts, 1899 (Reel 4816, Frame 991-992)
  - Miscellaneous non-art related clippings from New York Times, circa April 1900 (Reel 4816, Frame 1150)
  - Announcement for annual meeting of Municipal Art Society of New York, April 30, 1900 (Reel 4816, Frame 1154)
  - Clipping from New York Herald, Paris edition, "At the United States Embassy, Great Reception Given..." circa 1899-1900 (Reel 4816, Frame 1190)
  - Application and rules and regulations for space at the St. Louis Exposition and Music Hall Association, 1900 (Reel 4816, Frame 1213-1216)
  - Clippings, unidentified, with account of trip to Europe by Cornelia B. Sage, Director of Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, circa Oct. 1914 (Reel 4816, Frame 1296)
  - Clippings, unidentified obituaries for art patron and poet B.W. Woodward, of Lawrence, Kansas, circa October 1900, undated (Reel 4816, Frame 1308)
  - Invitation to exhibition opening, New York Water Color Club, November 9, 1900 (Reel 4816, Frame 1319)
  - Printed statement by John Ruskin "All Works of Taste (must bear a price...)," circa 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 12)
  - Invitation to Architectural League of New York exhibition, February 16, 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 43-44)
  - Checklist for the Fifth Annual Exhibition of the Society of Western Artists, Jan. 10-24, 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 52-54)
  - Checklist, special Exhibition of Early English Portraits, Book Bindings and Drawings from the McCormick, Lehmann, St. Louis Museum and Keppel & Co. collections (Reel 4817, Frame 55-57)
  - Commencement invitation and program, Amherst College, 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 183-184)
  - Invitation to press view of pan American Exposition, 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 201)
  - Proclamation by President William McKinley establishing the Louisiana Purchase International Exposition, August 20, 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 344)
  - Promotional material for Henry Romeike's clipping service, 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 397-399)
  - Circular of information re: the Department of Art, The Louisiana Purchase exhibition, circa 1901 (Reel 4817, Frame 485-489)
  - Clipping about Russian painter, Vassili Vassilitch Verestchagin, February 17, 1902 (Reel 4817, Frame 642)
  - Clipping, "The St. Louis Exhibition," July 22, 1902 (Reel 4817, Frame 795)
  - Invitation to National Sculpture Society's "Exhibition of Flowers and Sculpture," November, 1902 (Reel 4817, Frame 876-879)
  - Promotional material, Henry Romeike Press Cutting Bureau, 1902 (Reel 4817, Frame 929-933)
  - Clipping, "Emblem of St. Louis Fair," The World, November 26, 1902 (Reel 4817, Frame 973)
  - Clipping, "The National Academy of Design Exhibition," January 6, 1903 (Reel 4817, Frame 1031)
  - Promotional flyer for the American Art Annual, 1903 (Reel 4817, Frame 1162-1164)
  - Clipping "Art and Artists" from The Globe and Commercial Advertiser, Nov. 22, 1904 (Reel 4818, Frame 112)
  - Clipping, "European Art Boycott," unidentified, December 13, 1904 (Reel 4818, Frame 175)
  - Clipping, "A Few Cold Facts About Buffalo," from Buffalo Evening News, circa February, 1905 (Reel 4818, Frame 288)
  - Clipping, "Henry Wolf Honored," from The Boston Globe, May 15, 1905 (Reel 4818, Frame 467)
  - Clipping, "Sorolla at the Spanish Museum" and "Three Buffalo Books," unidentified, 1909 (Reel 4819, Frame 499)
  - Exposition material, 1884-1904, undated (Reel 4824)
    - Southern Exposition, 1885 (Reel 4824, Frame 109-167)
    - World's Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Reel 4824)
      - Miscellaneous printed memorabilia, 1893, undated (Reel 4824, Frame 171-185)
      - The Chicago World's Fair by Joel Cook (Reel 4824, Frame 186-197)
      - Department of Fine Arts, "Circular No. 3," 1892 (Reel 4824, Frame 198-204)
      - "A Leader and Teacher" [Halsey C. Ives], from The Art Folio (Reel 4824, Frame 205-206)
      - Miscellaneous printed matter (Reel 4824, Frame 207-223)
      - "The World's Fair and Industrial Art" by Alfred T. Goshorn from The Engineering Magazine, 1893 (Reel 4824, Frame 224-228)
      - "General Art Comments" [on World's Fair at Chicago] from Current Art & Architecture, 1893 (Reel 4824, Frame 233-242)
    - Catalogues
      - General Information, Department of Fine Arts, 1893 (Reel 4824, Frame 243-249)
      - World's Columbian Exposition, [priced] 1893 (Reel 4824, Frame 258-306)
      - Official World's Columbian Exposition, 1893 [illustrated, with corrections] (Reel 4824, Frame 307-400)
      - World's Columbian Exposition, Revised Catalogue Department of Fine Arts, 1893 with dedication to [Charles Ward] " Rhodes" (Reel 4824, Frame 401-514)
      - Loan Collection Foreign Masterpieces Owned in the United States, World's Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Reel 4824, Frame 515-528)
      - World's Columbian Exposition, Massachusetts Fine Art Exhibit, 1893, [annotated] (Reel 4824, Frame 529-533)
      - Exhibits of the State of New York at the World's Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Reel 4824, Frame 534-538)
      - The Magic City, A Portfolio of Original Photographic Views of the Great World's Fair, Vol. I, No. 3, Jan. 29, 1894 (Reel 4824, Frame 542-547)
      - The Magic City, A Portfolio of Original Photographic Views of the Great World's Fair, Vol. I, No. 5, Feb. 12, 1894 (Reel 4824, Frame 548-551)
      - The Magic City, A Portfolio of Original Photographic Views of the Great World's Fair, Vol. I, No. 11, March 26, 1894 (Reel 4824, Frame 552-555)
      - The Magic City, A Portfolio of Original Photographic Views of the Great World's Fair, Vol. I, No. 12, April 2, 1894 (Reel 4824, Frame 556-557)
    - St. Louis Expositions, 1894-1904 (Reel 4824)
      - Miscellaneous printed matter (Reel 4824, Frame 558-589)
      - Magazine clipping, "St. Louis Art Exhibition," The Arts, Vol. III. No. 4, Oct. 1894 (Reel 4824, Frame 569-572)
      - "The Great St. Louis Fair!" Suburban Home Journal, Vol. IX, No. I, Sept., 1895 (Reel 4824, Frame 577-580)
      - Magazine article from, St. Louis Life [Glasgow School] Sept., 1895 (Reel 4824, Frame 581-583)
      - Magazine article from St. Louis Life, Oct., 1895 (Reel 4824, Frame 588)
      - Promotional brochure, St. Louis Exposition (Reel 4824, Frame 589-590)
      - Printed Exposition material and applications (Reel 4824, Frame 591-604)
      - Catalogue of the Art Department, Saint Louis Exposition, 1894 [annotated with prices and purchasers of pictures; diagram of installation] (Reel 4824, Frame 603-656)
      - Catalogue of the Art Department, Saint Louis Exposition, 1895 [annotated with prices] (Reel 4824, Frame 657-724)
      - Art Department Catalogue, Saint Louis Exposiiton, 1896 [annotated] (Reel 4824, Frame 725-793)
      - Catalogue, Art Department, Saint Louis Exposition [annotated with prices], 1897 (Reel 4824, Frame 794-864)
      - Catalogue, Art Department, Saint Louis Exposition, 1898 (Reel 4824, Frame 865-930)
      - Catalogue, Art Department, Saint Louis Exposition, 1899 (Reel 4824, Frame 931-989)
    - Louisiana Purchase Exposition, 1904 (Reel 4824)
      - Brochure on conditions governing the design of an official emblem for the Louisiana Purchase Exposition (Reel 4824, Frame 991-1007)
      - Map and related information on Louisiana Purchase Exposition (Reel 4824, Frame 998-1000)
      - Circulars of Information Including the Classification and Rules and Regulations of the Department of Art (Reel 4824, Frame 1008-1017)
      - Miscellaneous printed matter (Reel 4824, Frame 1018-1043)
      - Circular No. 2 to Artists Eligible to Exhibit in The United States Section (Reel 4824, Frame 1021-1025)
      - Universal Exposition, Illustrated Handbook (Reel 4824, Frame 1044-1116)
      - Handbooks: Regulations Governing the Division of Exhibits of the Universal Exposition, St. Louis, 1904 Universal Exposition, Saint Louis, 1904, General Regulations; Rules and Regulations; Rules and Regulations Governing the System of Awards; Information Concerning Admission of Duty Free Exhibits, Quarantine of Animals, Patents, Trademarks and Copyrights (Reel 4825, Frame 001-79)
  - Exhibitions, Kurtz Collection and Estate, 1883-1990, undated (Reel 4825)
    - Miscellaneous exhibition catalogues: also includes checklists of shows of individual artists, museums, clubs including exhibitions of Charles M. Kurtz's personal collection (Reel 4825, Frame 83-396)
    - Annotated checklist and catalogue of Charles M. Kurtz estate sale; miscellaneous catalogues (Reel 4825, Frame 397-537)
  - Printed Material, 1873-1990, undated (Reel 4825)
    - Miscellaneous printed material: artwork for Academy Notes [NAD]; announcements, invitations, promotional material for M. de Munkacsy's Christ Before Pilot; articles on St. Louis School and Museum of Fine Arts; Ladies Art Association; The American Art Association; annual reports; programs; invitations (e.g. Art Institute of Chicago, Saint Louis Museum, The Japan Society, London); circulars, Paris Exposition of 1900; Academy Notes [Buffalo Fine Arts Academy], 1909 (Reel 4825, Frame 540-978)
    - posthumous printed tributes to and biographical sketches of the life of Charles M. Kurtz from Academy Notes, The Washington-Jeffersonian and Yale Center for British Art, 1990 ["Charles M. Kurtz and the Glasgow School"] (Reel 4825, Frame 979-992)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1882-1931, undated (Reel 4825)
    - Clippings include: biographical sketches of Charles M. Kurtz; articles on duty on art; biographical sketches and reviews of Joaquin Sorolla; pages from unidentified French Salon catalogue; reviews of American Academy Notes and The Art Union; press notices from "The Prize Fund Exhibition"; reviews of art exhibitions and related events at the Columbian exposition; St. Louis Exposition; Glasgow exhibitions; opening of Albright Gallery (Reel 4825, Frame 995-1075)
  - Calling Cards, undated (Reel 4825)
    - Friends, family, associates (Reel 4825, Frame 1078-1133)
    - Artists (Reel 4825, Frame 1136-1147)
- Photographs, 1898-1990, Series 10:
  The photographs in this series may be divided into two types: personal photographs of and by Charles M. Kurtz and photographs that record paintings in his collection or exhibitions that he administered. After his death, Kurtz was eulogized as being an early pioneer in the new art form of photography. His interest surfaces in letters written particularly in the 1890s. His associate, Charles Ward Rhodes, asks Kurtz's advice on things such as equipment, and indicates that Kurtz was considered knowledgeable on these subjects. In correspondence, Kurtz himself offers to send shipboard companions photographs he has taken. Very few photographs are identified as being taken by Kurtz. Many other photographs are most probably by him but not identified as such.
  Photographs of Kurtz, his family, friends, professional colleagues and artists, include Wm. Bóuguereau, Halsey C. Ives, Chas. H. Miller, Henry W. Ranger, F.K.M. Rehn, Chas. W. Rhodes, [Harry W.?] Watrous, and Charles Morris Young. Some identifications and other annotations are included with the photographs.
  - Snapshot, taken by Charles M. Kurtz, of Niagra Falls Sept. 4, 1898 (Reel 4816, Frame 374)
  - Snapshot, New Bronze Gallery at St. Louis Expo., May, 1899 (Reel 4816, Frame 784-5)
  - Snapshot of Joseph C. Spriggs, friend of Charles M. Kurtz, April, 1904 (Reel 4817, Frame 1361)
  - Charles Kurtz, family, friends, artists and professional colleagues, undated (Reel 4825, Frame 1152-1247)
  - Paintings in the Kurtz collection arranged alphabetically by artist, undated (Reel 4826, Frame 1-342)
  - Architecture and exhibitions/expositions, undated (Reel 4826)
    - Scotland, Louisiana Purchase Exposition grounds and art gallery installation, undated (Reel 4826, Frame 352-405)
    - Yale Center for British Art exhibition "The Glasgow School: The Charles M. Kurtz Collection" installation photographs, 1990 (Reel 4826, Frame 406-411)
    - Miscellaneous installation photographs of exhibitions, NAD [?] and Charles A. Green Gallery (Reel 4826, Frame 412-414)
- Photographs of Works Of Art, undated, Series 11:
  This series consists of oversized photographs of works of art and some original art work that Kurtz accummulated between circa 1876-1902. This material is in the Washington D.C. storage facility of the Archives of American Art and can be accessed by appointment only.
  - Portrait of Grimes by Matthew Jouett (Reel unfilmed)
  - Portrait of Carlyle (Reel unfilmed)
- Miscellany, undated, Series 12:
  This material consists of printed matter that was received after the collection was filmed, original letters and fragments that were badly scorched in a fire and could not be filmed, a letter-press book of correspondence by D.B. Kurtz and the glass plate negatives for portrait photographs of Julia and Charles Kurtz that were copied and filmed in Series X.
  - Miscellany (Reel unfilmed)